"What Are Hot Dogs and Burgers Made Of?"
What is in the hot dogs we eat?
A forensic study published
in the Annals
of Diagnostic Pathology
found bone, blood vessels,
nerves, cartilage, and skin.
But the kicker was that
the amount of actual meat
in a hot dog
was less than 10 percent.
But, of course,
the component of hot dogs
we should most care about
is the cancer risk,
and it contributes
to colorectal cancer,
the number one cancer killer
of nonsmokers.
That's why the prestigious
World Cancer Research Fund
and the American Institute
for Cancer Research
recommended
in their landmark report
that people simply avoid
processed meat.
The National Cattlemen's
Beef Association
chided the expert report
as "bad advice,"
saying that a different report
found no link
between meat and cancer.
A report that was,
in their words, "comprehensive"
by "independent scientists."
"How could the World Cancer
Research Fund research report
come to such a different
conclusion is perplexing,"
the beef association wrote.
But I found
that so-called "independent,
comprehensive review"
the beef industry
was referring to,
and be perplexed no more!
I was on it like brown on rice.
Let's compare.
The report funded
by a leading nonprofit
cancer research organization
took nine independent teams
of about 200 scientists
covering nearly 7,000 studies,
compiled by some of the top
cancer researchers in the world
and overseen by the likes
of the Food and Agriculture
Organization
of the United Nations
and the World Health
Organization,
producing a report
more than 500 pages long.
On the other hand,
this one was 2.5 pages,
written by a for-profit,
scientists-for-hire
consulting firm,
defenders of Big Tobacco
and virtually
every other toxic substance.
And this quote-unquote
"independent" study?
Bought and paid for
by the National Cattlemen's
Beef Association.
If you think
that took chutzpah,
wait until you see
what the pork industry did.
Smithfield, the largest
pork producer in the world,
launched the "Deli for the Cure"
campaign,
donating five cents
for every pound sold
of exactly the type of meat
found most causal for cancer.
What about burgers?
Anatomic pathologists
at the Cleveland Clinic
dissected fast-food burgers
to see what was inside.
Americans eat
five billion burgers a year,
and most consumers presume
that the hamburgers they eat
are composed primarily of meat.
But what did
the researchers find?
They analyzed burgers
from eight different
fast-food joints
and found them to contain
much of the same tissues
seen in hot dogs.
That's probably
not a good sign.
And two of the eight
fast-food burgers
contained parasites.
A quarter of the sample burgers
they looked at
had swarms
of these little parasites.
And researchers found
blood vessels,
nerves, cartilage.
What about actual meat?
What percentage
of a fast-food burger
is actually muscle flesh,
as opposed to these
other tissues, and parasites,
and fillers,
and everything else?
Meat content in the hamburgers
ranged from 2 percent
to 14.8 percent.
Just two percent meat?
They're practically vegetarian!
Part of that other 85
to 98 percent
that was not muscle meat
may be ammonia.
Thanks to some excellent
investigative reporting,
we learned that a company
developed a novel technique
for killing fecal bacteria:
injecting beef with ammonia.
The meat industry loved
this method so much,
ammonia found its way
into the majority
of hamburgers sold
across the United States.
The ammonia doesn't have to be
listed as an ingredient
because it's considered
a "processing aid."
In the U.S., it made its way
into all the big chains,
and millions of pounds
every year
were given to our kids
at school.
This is what the process
looks like,
producing what
one microbiologist
with the U.S. Department
of Agriculture
called pink slime,
saying he doesn't
even consider the stuff
to be meat.
Not even good enough
for prisoners in Georgia.
It was sent back
because the meatloaf stank
like window cleaner.
Why would we feed this
to schoolchildren?
School lunch officials said
they ultimately agreed
to use the ammonia-treated meat
because it shaved
about three cents off the cost
of making a pound
of ground beef.
The process is banned
in Canada.
Production and consumption
of pink slime
is strictly prohibited
in Europe.
In the United States, however,
the meat industry sued ABC News
for its story about it,
and though ABC News maintained
that its reporting
was accurate,
ABC News backed down
after facing the potential
for billions of dollars
of damages.
And upon industry request,
the USDA simply reclassified
the product
as 100% ground beef,
displaying the raw power
of Big Slime.